From their perch on the International Spaceô
Station, astronauts have spent two decades sharingô ô
a story about Earth as they see it from above.ô
Like the directors of any film those astronautô ô
storytellers have a cast and crew workingô
behind the scenes to help them tell that story.ô ô
The Earth Science and Remote Sensing group (ESRS) here at Johnson Space Center is primarily designedô ô
to support the International Space Stationô
program. Our job there is twofold. One, it's toô ô
run, manage the Crew Earth Observations Facilityô
on the ISS. That's the handheld crew imagery ofô
the Earth. The other is to serve as subject matterô
experts to the ISS program for matters of remoteô sensing. ô
Though the photos shot from the spaceô
station can be quite beautiful, they're mostlyô ô
shot for practical reasons. Astronaut photographyô
is a science product designed to help everyoneô ô
from academic and government researchers toô
resource managers and conservation groups toô ô
educators and students. The photographs documentô
changes in our cities and remote ecosystems,ô ô
in polluted waters, and pristine landscapes. Theyô
have been used to study everything from urbanô ô
development and economics to unusual electricalô
discharges in the atmosphere. These snapshots haveô ô
been used to observe fishing boats and coralô
reefs, calving icebergs, and vast inland deltas.ô ô
Though handheld cameras are not as precise asô
robotic imagers they provide a nice complement.ô ô
Most satellites view the world at the same timeô
and same resolution with each pass. But each Spaceô Station
orbit brings different viewing angles,ô
different times of day, and different lighting.ô ô
We've had a number of external science requestsô
for nighttime imagery of various cities forô ô
investigators who are looking at light pollutionô
and seeing how that's affecting biodiversity in their cities. ô ô
The Earth Science and Remoteô
Sensing team manages dozens of requests forô ô
images with new ones coming in weekly.
We'veô got this long list of maybe 50 to 100 on any given day that we will parse through,
and the way weô decide which target we will ask for the next day is,
we'll see where the ISS is. We'll take intoô
account lighting conditions, whether it's lightô ô
enough for daytime targets or dark enough forô
nighttime targets.
Once we have what they can see, then we'll filter that for predicted weather,ô cloud cover for that area.
There's no point inô ô asking them for a target if they're not going toô be able to see it.
With a new sunrise and sunset every 90 minutes, the astronauts have 16 chancesô to see what the planet and its people are doing.
But life on the Space Station bringsô
its own sort of sunrise and sunset.
Flight surgeons say do not ask for anythingô
during their sleep period which is a thirdô ô
of the day. That's a full eight hours. But youô
may ask for everything between six o'clock andô ô
nine, 21:30, in the evening which includes theirô
getting up time, breakfast time, and the workô day. ô
And bedtime, supper time, brush your teeth time.
Having considered astronauts schedules and the viability of each target,
the Earth Observationsô team chooses a few targets for each day.
They assemble guides and maps so the astronautsô
can quickly orient themselves.
They send the target plans to payload operations at Marshallô Space Flight Center where photo ops are reviewed,ô
approved, and added to the ISS workday.
They willô provide for us useful information to help give us
maybe cues off the surface of the Earth that willô
help train our eye to go find a specific targetô ô
that otherwise would be very difficult to find inô
there. They want that target for specific reasons.ô ô
Preflight they will have trained us in thatô
and why those elements of that data are soô ô
important, which helps us in the technique thatô
we might apply in getting the photograph. ô
Perhaps the hardest part of theô
job for the Earth Observations teamô ô
comes after the astronauts put down theô
camera. Anywhere from 100 to 10,000 imagesô ô
are sent down to ground control every day.
Onceô that gets downlinked, it gets ingested into our system
and I'll look through those and seeô
if they're appropriate to send to the researchers.
Though computers are now part of the process, forô
most of the past 20 years those photos have beenô ô
sorted by human hands and eyes.
That's the highestô priority for us, to catalog them.
And by cataloging I mean adding descriptive metadata to the image.
Things like what geographic features can you seeô in this image. That helps then when it's fedô into our online database.
That's what enablesô ô people to search for those images.
Every photoô has some basic information about the location.
But since the ground team did not shoot the photosô
they have to decipher what can be seen in them.ô ô
It is a monumentally important but monumentallyô
time-consuming job. Because these images areô ô
taken by the astronauts, they're looking out of theô
cupola with a with a handheld camera. They can lookô ô
in any direction they want. We know exactly whereô
the space station was when they took the picture.ô ô
So we kind of have a general idea ofô
where it could possibly be. We know whatô ô
hemisphere it is in for instance. But we don'tô
necessarily know which way they were looking. ô
It is a rich decades-long catalog of theô
dynamic changes, forces, and beauties ofô ô
our planet. It always struck me how littleô
the remote sensing community used this data.ô ô
And primarily that was because it historicallyô
has been a difficult data set to use.
One of the focuses that I've had leading this group has been,ô okay, we need we need to bring new tools to bear toô ô
make this dataset more useful.
Stefanov's teamô has been working to automate more of its tasks using new software and computing techniquesô like machine learning.
If we have machines thatô can identify these features automatically, thenô our database becomes that much more searchableô
and the public can use it more easily, scientistsô
can find exactly what they're looking for.
Lambert and colleagues are now training computers toô
detect and recognize certain features on the land,ô ô
in the sky, and on the ocean. They're using neuralô
networks to help machines quickly identify photosô ô
with a lake or a sea, the limb of theô
Earth or the Moon, a crater or a city.ô ô
They're particularly focused on clouds.
Oneô problem that people have that are doing GIS is that you've got our imagery, and it's great, butô it's got clouds in it.
And those clouds obscure what you're interested in looking at. If we have anô algorithm that produces a mask where every pixelô ô
is labeled as either clouds or no clouds, that
label can be applied to the whole image and theyô ô
can subtract the clouds from their analysis, soô
that way they are ignored.
Astronaut photographs have been used for some scientific studies and forô inspiring people to better appreciate the planet.ô ô
But the Earth Observations team believesô
those photos could have even wider use,ô ô
and they want to make sureô
the world sees more of them.